Cynthia Ellen Elbaum Papers, 1994-2012
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Cynthia Ellen Elbaum papers
1984-2012
Elbaum, Cynthia Ellen, 1966-1994
MS 560
7 boxes (5.25 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Photojournalist. The Papers document Elbaum's career as a photojournalist, notably in Chechnya during the war with the Soviet Union and include biographical information and photographs.
Cynthia Ellen Elbaum grew up in Ashfield, Massachusetts and attended the School of the Museum of Fine Arts in Boston before graduating from Smith College in 1989, where she pursued her interest in photography and also studied Russian. She taught English while studying on a scholarship in Moscow, and then moved to New York where she taught English to Russian refugees. Elbaum began her career as a photojournalist in 1992, after she witnessed dead bodies on a Moscow street following Boris Yeltsin's takeover of the Russian parliament. On December 1, 1994, she went to Chechnya to cover the gathering of Russian forces there; she was killed three weeks later by a Russian bomb.
The Cynthia Ellen Elbaum Papers document Elbaum's career as a photojournalist, notably in Chechnya during the war with the Soviet Union. It consists primarily of biographical information, correspondence and documentation of photo exhibits compiled and curated, respectively, after her untimely death in 1994.
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
This collection has not been fully processed and therefore may be difficult to use.
Original audiovisual materials and master copies are closed. Research copies are available.
History of the Collection
Search Terms
Chechnia (Russia)--History--Civil War, 1994-1996; Russia (Federation)--Politics and government--1991- --Sources; Photojournalists--Biography--Sources; Elbaum, Cynthia Ellen, 1966-1994
- ACCESSION I.
  - Biographical information: obituaries, tributes, photographs, articles, VHS tapes, and clippings circa 1994-95, undated (Box 1)
  - Diary (spiral bound notebook, only a few pages of writing) 1994 (Box 1)
  - Jude Elbaum (mother of Cynthia): correspondence about Cynthia Elbaum circa 1995-97 (Box 1)
  - Elbaums photojournalism career (Box 1)
  - Information about exhibits of Elbaums photographs circa 1994-97 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, clippings, articles, VHS tape, and audiocassette circa 1996-2000 (Box 1)
  - Clippings, articles, newspapers and VHS tape 1994-2000 (Box 2)
  - Photographs and negatives circa 1992-94 (Box 3)
  - OVERSIZE MATERIALS
    - Clippings, and photographs from exhibit 1995-97 (Box 4)
    - Mounted exhibit of Elbaums photographs 1997 (Box 5)
  - ON SHELF
    - Mounted exhibit of Elbaums photographs 1997 (Box 5)
- ACCESSION II.
  - VHS tapes (3) (Box 1)
    - Suzannahs Christining Party, A Cynthia Elbaum Video 1989 (Box 1)
    - Cynthias 27th birthday (Box 1)
    - Cynthia - Christmas 1992 (Box 1)
  - Super 8 (Ektachrome) (Box 1)
    - Unmarked (Box 1)
  - 8 mm undated (Box 1)
    - Unmarked (5) (Box 1)
    - Peace Bagota (Box 1)
    - Florida  Train  Sunrise  Gulls(?) (Box 1)
    - The Dubious Shopper  The Film(?) (Box 1)
    - Diner(?) (Box 1)
    - Still Life (Box 1)
    - Road(?) footage (shit) (Box 1)
    - #67  clouds  CEK(?) & diego (Box 1)
    - #67  Amusement Park (Box 1)
    - Martha (Box 1)
    - #90 (Box 1)
    - #90  Malarians (Box 1)
    - Gregor (Box 1)
- ACCESSION III.
  - Personal correspondence 1991-1994 (Box 1)
  - Slides, photographs, and negatives early 1990s (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings and photographs 1984 (Box 1)
  - Betsy Beebes Collection of Cynthias Info. & Communication with her 1994-2007, undated (Box 1)
  - Two journals undated, circa early-1990s (Box 1)
  - DVD (1): Cynthia Elbaum: A Life in Photographs, Grand Prize Winner, Ashfield Film Festival 2012 (Box 1)
  - CD (1): For Cynthia, Tony Jillson undated (Box 1)
  - OVERSIZE MATERIALS
    - 1 FedEx envelope (Box 1)
    - Newspaper articles, originals and color photocopies (Box 1)